hello streaming data is everywhere and its growth
seems unstoppable activity from social networks
website analytics and sensors and iot devices
generates a constant flow of new data coming at
us from a huge number of sources in this video
we'll see how redis can help us capture manage
and make sense of these large and constantly
moving volumes of data right out of the box
streaming data is data that's generated
continuously often from a large number of
concurrent sources one useful way of thinking
about a stream is as a series of events
every entry in the stream represents a new event
for example you can imagine recording a stream of
weather sensor readings at a given location every
entry in the stream might consist of a temperature
a humidity measurement and the wind direction
and speed because streams and events are such
a useful abstraction and occur so often in the
real world redis provides a data structure called
a stream in the rest of this video i'm going to
introduce some streaming concepts and then i'll
demonstrate some of the basic commands you can
use to manipulate streams and redis so let's
start with concepts in a distributed application
architecture the components that write to a stream
are called producers the data they generate
is added to a stream with each entry having a
unique identifier and its specific fields at the
other end of the stream are one or more consumers
these consumer processes read entries from
the stream and process them as necessary
what's interesting is that you can have more
than one consumer reading from your stream
each consumer has its own role for example one
type of consumer might create notifications
in a mobile application when certain trigger
values are seen in the data another consumer
might write all entries to a data warehouse for
later analysis while a third consumer could act
as a producer for yet another stream adding
only a subset of the entries to the new stream
producers and consumers often operate at different
rates the stream acts as a buffer between them as
well as the decoupling mechanism this means
that producers and consumers don't directly
communicate with each other so don't need to
know anything about each other's implementations
now let's talk about the reddit stream data
structure itself a reddit stream is a data
structure that behaves like an appendally log
once added an entry in a stream is immutable
each entry in a reddest stream has a unique id
and by default these ids are timestamp prefixed
this means that a reddest stream
keeps entries ordered as a time series
stream entries look a lot like a redis
hash each is a set of name value pairs
it's also worth noting that reader streams are
schema-less while each stream entry has to have
at least one name value pair they don't all have
to use the same structure redis allows consumers
to read stream entries in order consumers can also
efficiently seek to any entry within the stream
so enough theory let's look at redis
streams in action we'll see how they
fit into a common use case for streaming data
systems recording real-time crowdsourced data
imagine we're building a mobile app that allows
users to check in at all sorts of businesses
public spaces and workplaces users provide star
ratings based on their experience at each location
each time a user checks in they'll pick out
their location from a list our app provides
they'll then select a star rating from 0 to 5
and the app will send this data along with their
user id to a server users earn prize draw entries
for each check-in and we periodically offer cool
prizes to randomly drawn winners this incentive
encourages users to check in often improving
their chance of winning a typical check-in can
be represented as a set of name-value pairs here
we have a check in for user id 99 at venue id
103 the user decided to give this venue 4 stars
readings from our many users are sent continuously
to our servers and those servers produce entries
into our redis stream once this fire hose
of jumbled data is added to a reddit stream
we can begin to organize and make sense of
it let's see how each check-in finds its way
into a reddit stream first like other redis data
structures a stream is associated with a redis key
we'll use the key check-ins to identify the
incoming stream of check-in data the x-add command
adds a new entry to a stream here we're adding
an entry to the check in stream from user 90781
this user is visiting location 348 and
rating it three stars the asterisk in the
exact command tells redis to assign this entry
a unique id consisting of the current timestamp
plus a sequence number exside returns the
id that redis is assigned to the new entry
the first part is the timestamp in milliseconds
and the second is a sequence number
since stream ids must be unique this convention
ensures that we can add as many entries as we need
in the same millisecond now that we have check-ins
flooding into our stream it's time to think about
how the business can make sense of them as
redis assigns each entry a timestamp based id
one way that a consumer can view the stream is as
a time series here we're using the x range command
to read entries in the check-in stream that fall
between the specified start and end time stamps
x-range returns each entry whose id
falls within the specified time period
entries are returned in
order with the oldest first
to limit the number of entries returned
we can use the optional count modifier
if we want the most recent entries first
we can use the x rev range command instead
note that here we specify the time period in the
reverse order with the end time stamp coming first
and if we don't know what time period the
entries in the stream cover we can use both
x range and x rev range with a special plus
and minus operators to represent the highest
and lowest timestamps respectively here we're
retrieving the oldest two entries in the stream
but really streams are all about real-time data
consumption so we want to build consumers that
continuously receive data we could achieve this
by pulling the stream using the x-range command
but that's inefficient ideally we want a
command that lets us consume the stream
blocking when we've seen all the
entries until a producer adds new ones
this is one of the use cases for the x read
command xreed can consume one or more streams
optionally blocking until new entries appear here
i'm calling x-read against the check-in stream
x-read consumes the stream returning entries whose
ids are greater than the one provided here i'm
asking for all entries with an id greater than
0 the beginning of the stream and redis returns
the entire stream we'll need to note the id of
the latest entry for subsequent calls to x read
we can also invoke x-read in a way that blocks the
consumer until new entries are added to the stream
to use xread in a blocking context i'll
provide the last entry id for my previous call
i'll also specify i want to consume a single
new entry and how long to block in case the
stream doesn't yet contain any entries newer than
the one whose id i'm supplying here i'm telling
x-read to block for up to 5000 milliseconds or 5
seconds when i run this command it blocks because
no new messages with higher ids than the one
i provided have yet been added to the stream
while the consumer is blocked i'll use a second
redis cli session to add a new entry to the stream
as soon as i do that the consumer unblocks
and xreed returns the newly added entry
if no new entries have been added
in a 5 second blocking period
xreed would have returned a nil response i
could then choose the block again or give
up trying and do something else it's important
to note that consuming the stream using x range
x rev range and x read doesn't remove entries as
they are retrieved entries remain in the stream
allowing other consumers to read the entire
data set each processing it in its own way
here one consumer is maintaining running average
star ratings a second writes the entries to a data
warehouse and a third adds entries to another
stream if the star rating is below a triggered
threshold so if new check-ins are constantly
pouring into our stream and consumers reading them
aren't removing them then how do we contain this
seemingly never-ending growth remember that a
stream models independently log this means that
the order and content of entries can't be modified
once they've been added however redis supports a
trimming strategy to manage a stream's memory use
let's assume our stream now contains tens of
thousands of entries and that we need to control
its growth trimming a stream removes its oldest
entries that is those of the lowest timestamp
ids this frees up memory associated with these
entries let's see how that works in practice redis
commands can be used to trim a stream the first of
these is xtrim this command can be run at any time
and trims the stream's length to a specified new
length here we're using xtrim to trim our check in
stream to a new maximum length of 10 000 entries
the command returns the number of entries removed
in this case we removed 20 000 in one
of the oldest entries from the stream
leaving the newest ten thousand the second way to
trim the oldest entries from the stream is to do
so while adding a new entry with the exact command
and this is the more common strategy if we know
that we always want to keep the check in stream to
a length of 10 000 or less then we simply specify
that on every call to x ad like you see here
as you saw earlier xad returns the id of the
entry that was added but doesn't tell us what the
new length of the stream is for that we can use
xlan and we see that the stream has been capped
to 10 000 entries including the newly added one
there's a lot more to reddit streams of what
i've presented here so if you're interested in
learning more you should check out redis streams
our free online course from redis university
i know streams can seem like a fire hose
of information so thanks for sticking with
me and forwarding this river together
happy learning and see you again soon